# PRANJAL PATEL

pranjalp@bu.edu | +1 (732) 763-2940 | <a href="https://github.com/pranj999">www.linkedin.com/in/pranj999</a> https://github.com/pranj999 | 17 Balboa Lane, Franklin Park, NJ 08823 | http://pranj999.pythonanywhere.com/

#### **SUMMARY**

Research-oriented professional with a strong background in Computer Science with strong skills in data preprocessing, data processing, database management, data visualization, machine learning algorithms, neural networks, and data science. The short-term goal is to leverage strong data science skills to fill the position of Data Scientist or Data Analyst effectively. My long-term goal is to grow as a Machine Learning Engineer. Strengths include excellent verbal skills, sterling teamwork, well organized, ability to grasp ideas quickly, and hunger to learn something new from anyone.

#### **EDUCATION**

## Boston University | Boston, MA

Sep 2021 – Jan 2023

Master of Science in Computer Science, Overall GPA: 3.48

 Relevant Courses: Data Science with Python, Machine learning, Web analytics and mining, Foundation of Machine learning with R.

## **SRM institute of science and technology |** Chennai, India

Jun 2017 – Jun 2021

Bachelor of Technology in Computer Science, Overall Percentage: 80

Relevant Courses: Analysis of algorithms, Data mining, and analytics, Operating systems, Artificial Intelligence,
 Discrete Mathematics, Database management systems

### **PROJECTS EXECUTED**

# Disaster Tweet Classification, Boston University

Mar 2022 — Apr 2022

- Build two machine learning models to correctly classify tweets if they are related to any kind of disaster or not. The first model used a count vector and Random Forest while the second used Bidirectional LSTM. The accuracy of both models was compared and useful inferences were extracted.
- The accuracy of the Random Forest was just 57% whereas, the accuracy of the LSTM model was 75%. In addition, used a TF-IDF vector to generate a vector matrix of tweets and used randomized SVD for topic extraction. Stack: NumPy, Pandas, Keras, Sklearn, Nltk, Matplotlib

## **Exploratory Data Analysis, Boston University**

Oct 2021 — Dec 2021

Data on Boston Crime rates were used to identify patterns of crime in the city of Boston. Important inferences
were made from the data. Delivered an R markdown file as a presentation. Collaborated as a team to analyze
the data and draw meaningful conclusions. The team utilized various statistical techniques and visualizations to
uncover trends and correlations within the crime rates. Stack: R markdown, DPLYR, ggplot2, tidyverse, ggmap,
and dev tools.

Sentiment Analysis of social media, Boston University

Mar 2022 — Apr 2022

• I utilized a trained machine learning model to detect the sentiment of people's reactions on social media. By implementing various algorithms and comparing their accuracy, I was able to identify the sentiment of the posts. I also incorporated natural language processing techniques to preprocess the text data and extract relevant features. Additionally, I used cross-validation techniques to ensure the reliability of my model's performance across different datasets. Stack: Sklearn, NumPy, Pandas, Matplotlib, Seaborn, AdaBoost, Logistic Regression, MLPClassifier, LDA, Gradient Boosting, and KNN.

Portfolio Project Jun 2023 — Jul 2023

The Django Portfolio Project is a static web application that elegantly and interactively displays my
professional portfolio, abilities, and accomplishments. The project offers users a user-friendly interface to
explore my work, learn about my experience, and get in touch with me for prospective partnerships and
opportunities.

It was created using the robust Python web framework Django. As the project's lone developer, I made use
of Django's flexibility to build a dynamic and unique portfolio platform that showcases my
accomplishments and expresses my professional and out-of-work identity. Stack: Django, Tailwind CSS,
JavaScript,

# PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

### Data Analyst Intern, Shift4, Allentown, PA

Jun 2022— Aug 2022

- Liaised with developers to automate the process of verification of the data provided by writing a script in SQL and Python. SQL Server was used to manage the data. Delivered important inferences using Tableau.
- Using R performed an Exploratory data analysis on a different dataset and using R markdown delivered a presentation.

## Business Data Analyst, Param Consultancy and IT Services, Iselin, NJ

Feb 2023—Present

- Conducted comprehensive data analysis using SQL, Excel, and data visualization tools to identify trends, patterns, and correlations in the datasets provided. Created interactive dashboards and reports to communicate findings effectively, aiding stakeholders in understanding performance metrics and making informed decisions.
- Assembled and led a team of developers, providing clear directions and setting project goals. Conducted
  regular team meetings to update progress, address challenges, and ensure alignment with the project's
  objectives. Facilitated a collaborative and innovative team culture, fostering creativity and problem-solving,
  and successfully delivered the Django website within the agreed timeline and budget, meeting all specified
  requirements.

## **PROFESSIONAL SKILLS**

- *Computer*: Python, C++, C, SQL, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, R, Tableau, Django, MS Office (Excel, PowerPoint), Data Science Libraries, Neural networks
- *Tools*: MySQL, Git, Keras, TensorFlow
- Language: English (fluent), Gujarati (native), Hindi (fluent)